Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף Daf is מ"ם Mem 40.
We pick up in the middle of ל"ט עמוד ב׳ Lamed Tet
Amud Bet right after
the parenthesis about twenty lines down. The line starts with the word
תנן התם. Tnan hasam. So תנן התם. Tnan hasam. So we're dealing
with the מצוה Mitzvah of יבום Yibbum and חליצה, Chalitzah, the משנה
Mishna obviously prefers יבום Yibbum to חליצה Chalitzah and then speaks about
prioritizing also the older brother before the younger one and the גמרא
Gemara had some type of some discussion about which of those was
more important, to prefer יבום Yibbum or to prefer the older. Clearly,
the weight is on the idea that we prefer יבום Yibbum even
if it means יבום Yibbum of a younger one before חליצה Chalitzah
of an older. And then a similar discussion about whether there was
a preference in terms of חליצה, Chalitzah, whether it was older or
younger. But clearly יבום Yibbum is preferred to חליצה. Chalitzah. Now let's
take a look as we question or problematize that issue. תנן התם,
Tnan hasam, we taught over
there: מצות יבום קודמת למצות חליצה. Mitzvas Yibbum kodemes lemitzvas chalitzah. The
מצוה Mitzvah of יבום, Yibbum, this is in כתובות Kesubos ironically,
this הלכה. Halacha. So the מצוה Mitzvah of this משנה, Mishna, the
מצוה Mitzvah of יבום Yibbum precedes the מצוה Mitzvah of חליצה. Chalitzah.
Okay, that's pretty implicit. בראשונה שהיו מתכוונים לשם מצוה. Barishona shehayu miskavnim
leshem mitzvah. That was originally where the intent where people were doing
it for the right purposes. People did יבום, Yibbum, meaning men did
יבום, Yibbum, because of the מצוה. Mitzvah. עכשיו שאין מתכוונים לשם מצוה.
Achshav she'ein miskavnim leshem mitzvah. Now they do יבום Yibbum for other
reasons. Now what are the other reasons? So we'll see what the
גמרא Gemara says, but the most likely other reason I would say
is what the next משנה Mishna is about to tell us, which
is that the man who does יבום Yibbum gets his brother's property.
So that would certainly be an ulterior motive. So now that they're
doing יבום, Yibbum, yeah, well that will get you, now that they're
doing יבום Yibbum not for the purpose of מצוה, Mitzvah, אמרו מצות
חליצה קודמת למצות יבום. Amru mitzvas chalitzah kodemes lemitzvas yibbum. We say
that the מצוה Mitzvah of חליצה Chalitzah comes first.
So here, so this is obviously a very critical issue, is there
a shifting of prioritizing instead of יבום Yibbum before חליצה, Chalitzah, חליצה
Chalitzah before יבום Yibbum because people are not doing it לשם מצוה?
Leshem mitzvah? And what would constitute not לשם מצוה? Leshem mitzvah? Okay,
so that's what we have in the משנה Mishna over there. So
אמר רב, Amar Rav, and now let's see how that issue develops
about the question of whether we actually do now give preference to
חליצה. Chalitzah. So אמר רב אין כופין. Amar Rav: Ein kofin. We
don't force. Now what does that mean we don't force? So רש"י
Rashi says what it means that we don't force is that we
don't force it,
רש"י Rashi says it means that if the, we don't force the
couple if both of them want to do יבום, Yibbum, we don't
force חליצה. Chalitzah. So the way רש"י Rashi reads this is that
yes, we still prefer חליצה, Chalitzah, but we allow יבום Yibbum as
an option. And if both of them want to do יבום, Yibbum,
we don't protest it. Now רש"י, Rashi, by the way, also makes
a very important point, because until now the woman has been completely
silent and it's all been about the man and what the man
wants to do. So I do want to read you a רש"י
Rashi here that makes a point relating to that. He says, if
three lines from the top if you look in the middle of
the line, רש"י Rashi says the following: ומיהו היכא דהוא צבי ליבומי.
Umiha heicha dihuta tzevi leyabumei. If he wants to do יבום. Yibbum.
ואי אמרה לא בעינא ליה. Ve'ee amra lo ba'ina lei. I don't
want him. ואמרה דברים ניכרים. V'amra devarim nikarim. And she says a
good reasonable reason why she doesn't want to marry him. So אם
צינו לאתויי ולומר לו חלוץ לה על מנת שתתן לך מאתים זוז.
Im tzeinu le'atuyei v'lomar lo chalos la'amnas shetitan lecha masayim zuz. Now
this is also deeply disturbing because on the one hand רש"י Rashi
is saying that we basically accede to her wishes and we do
not allow יבום Yibbum if she does not want it. On the
other hand, rather than initially just making him do חליצה, Chalitzah, we
basically first try to bribe him. And as we know today, the
whole idea of extortion around issues of a גט, Get, you know,
well I'll give it if you give me enough money. So anyway,
so already here you have some of the seeds to that here.
So we're going to protect her and make sure חליצה Chalitzah is
done. The first thing we're going to try to do is try
to sort of influence him and say she'll give you two hundred
זוז. Zuz. אמטי ליה. Amatze lei. Then we sort of influence him
that way. ואם לאו. Ve'im lo. And if that doesn't work. כפינן
ליה וחלץ. Kafinan lei v'chalatz. We force him and we force him
to do חליצה. Chalitzah. דמה ששת מנין ליבמה שנפלה לפני מוכה שחין
שאין כופין אותה. D'mah sheshis minayin liyivama shenafla lifnei mukei shechin she'ein
kofin osah. How do you know if a sister-in-law falls before a
brother-in-law who is like disgusting physically, repulsive, we don't force her? And
now רש"י Rashi says and he gives a פסוק. Pasuk. And then
רש"י Rashi says ולא תימא מוכה שחין דוקא. V'lo teima mukei shechin
davka. It's not only something that's clearly completely repulsive and intolerable. אלא
כל אמתא שתתן לדבריה. Ella kol amasa shetitan lidevareha. Any reasonable reason
that she gives. So okay, so that's a question. But alright, so
anyway רש"י Rashi is very important in that he
is sort of saying and we'll see that גמרא Gemara later on
and when we get to it, but some of that is also
in כתובות, Kesubos, so but רש"י Rashi is very important because until
now the woman has completely been silent. It's all about do you
want to do יבום, Yibbum, do you want to do חליצה, Chalitzah,
all talking to the brothers. רש"י Rashi here has introduced us to
the fact that you need that if she refuses, even any reasonable
explanation, it is a legitimate and we will not allow for יבום
Yibbum to take place. We will make sure that חליצה Chalitzah is
what takes place, either by bribery or by force. But the way
we're just reading the first רש"י Rashi here on the עמוד ב׳.
Amud Bet. Okay. So that is what he introduces, that's not directly
the. is although we have said that we prioritize חליצה chalitzah over
יבום, yibum, that's what we've just said in reverse to the way
the משנה mishnah framed it and the way initially used to be,
we will still allow יבום, yibum, and we won't prevent it as
long as both sides want to do יבום. yibum. So that's how
רש״י Rashi is reading it. I will get to how תוספות Tosafos
reads this גמרא gemara in a minute. Let's make a little headway.
So, so that's the way רש״י Rashi is. Yes, חליצה chalitzah comes
first, but we will allow יבום yibum if both sides want it.
כי אתו לקמיה דרב, ki asu lekamei deRav, now that's what רב
Rav said. So when a couple would come to רב, Rav, אמר
להו, amar lehu, he would say to them, אי בעית חלוץ אי
בעית יבם. iba'is chalot iba'is yabem. I don't know how to pronounce
that word... יבם. yabem. Anyway, so he, right. So here, it's even
more than, thank you, it's even more than we don't, you know,
we don't break it up if they want to do יבום. yibum.
It's, he almost, but like we say do חליצה chalitzah and then
we'll allow it if they want to do יבום. yibum. Here he
actually presents both as options. So it's even more allowing יבום yibum
as a possibility. The only thing is as we know when, you
know, people take their, you know, they do these surveys, and half,
you know, and the the response can shift 20 points just based
on how the question is framed. You know, so here, he frames
that he says, "Do you want to do חליצה chalitzah or maybe
you'd want to do יבום?" yibum? So by putting, he put יבום
yibum second, but that is the only way חליצה chalitzah is prioritized.
So we go by saying not only do we not prevent, do
we not break it up if they want to do יבום, yibum,
not only do we not force them not to do יבום, yibum,
but we even put it out as an option, we just put
out the חליצה chalitzah option first. אי בעית חלוץ אי בעית
יבם. iba'is chalot iba'is yabam. בדידך תלא רחמנא. bedidech tala rachmana. But
then look at this, he actually says, it's your choice! The תורה
Torah leaves it up to you. ואם לא יחפוץ האיש, ve'im lo
yachpotz ha'ish, if the person doesn't want to, then he does חליצה.
chalitzah. הא אם חפץ, ha im chafetz, but if you want to,
אי בעית חלוץ אי בעית יבם, iba'i chalot iba'i yalem, you can
take your choice. You can do חליצה chalitzah or you can do
יבום. yibum. So, of course, the גמרא gemara תורה Torah frames it
the opposite, do יבום, yibum, however, you could choose not to. But
nevertheless, this seems to really go against the idea that חליצה chalitzah
comes first, 'cause it's hard to say I, you know, okay, it's
very nice to say that people don't do it for the right
reason, but the תורה Torah still has prioritized יבום. yibum. So it's
nice for us to say, yeah, but there's problems with it, we're
going to prioritize... so how do you deal with the fact that
we want חליצה... chalitzah... we have problems with יבום yibum but the
תורה Torah still is prioritizing it. So here what you have is
it's sort of put out as relatively equal options with a slight...
a slight maybe influencing towards חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, so that's... that's what
רב Rav used to do. All right, so give them options, but
certainly not stand in the way if they want to do יבום
yibum and maybe put חליצה chalitzah first, but really tell them they
can choose, they have both options. ואף רב יהודה סבר אין כופין.
ve'af Rav Yehuda savar ein kofin. Even רב יהודה Rav Yehuda held
that you do not force, again the way רש״י Rashi reads this
to mean, you don't force them to do חליצה, chalitzah, you allow
them to do יבום. yibum. מדאשכחן רב יהודה בגיטא דחליצה. mid'askin Rav
Yehuda be-gita de-chalitzah. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda established this is the language
of the גט get of חליצה. chalitzah. Now that's a funny phrase,
a גט get of חליצה, chalitzah, but the word גט get really
means a document. גט get does not necessarily mean a divorce, it
means a writ, and this basically would be the בית דין's beis
din record that a חליצה chalitzah took place and that could later
be used as evidence that this woman could produce, you know, right,
it was kept in the... it was kept in the records that...
that could produce to say that look, I'll show you חליצה chalitzah
took place, I should be allowed to get married. And here's the
language he established in that writ of חליצה. chalitzah. איך פלונית בת
פלוני, ech plonis bas ploni, איך ech means we testify. Normally it
would be preceded with the word אנן סהדי איך. anan sahadei ech.
Right, we testify that this woman, פלונית בת פלוני, plonis bas ploni,
this woman, you know, שרה Sarah the daughter of
ראובן, Reuven, אקרביה פלוני יבמה קדמנא, akravyas ploni yabma kadmana, brought so-and-so
her brother-in-law in front of us, right, because the woman in the
תורה Torah is the one who brings the brother-in-law, right, to the
בית דין. beis din. לבית דינא, leBeis Dina, to the בית דין.
beis din. ואישתמודעינו הוא, ve'ishtemod'einu hu, and we recognized him, דאחוה דמיתנא
מאבא ניהו, de-achua de-misna me'abba nihu, that he was a paternal brother
to the dead person. ואמרי ליה, ve'amri leh, and we said to
him, אי צבית ליבם יבם, itzavis leyabem yabem, if you want to
do יבום yibum do יבום, yibum, ואם לא, ve'im lo, and if
you don't want to do יבום, yibum, איטלא לרגליך דימינא, itla leglakh
de-yamina, sort of stick out your leg, דימינא, de-yamina, your right leg
to her, ואיטלא לרגליה דימינא, ve'itla leglah de-yamina, and he stuck out
his right leg to her, ושרת סיניה מעל רגלוהי, vesharas sinei me'al
raglohi,
and she undid the... the shoe from his leg, וירקת באנפוהי, veyarkas
be'anpohi, and
she spat in his face or in his presence, רוקא דמיתחזי לבית
דינא, rok d'miskhazi leBeis Dina, a spit that was visible to the
בית דין, beis din, על ארעא, al ara, and it spat on
the ground, not actually at his face, in front of him but
on the ground. ורב חייא בר אביי מסיים בה משמיה דרב יהודה,
veRav Chiya bar Avya mesayeim bah mishmei deRav Yehuda, and רב חייא
בר אביי Rav Chiya bar Avya adds the following line in the
name of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. ואקרינוהו מה דכתיב בספר אורייתא דמשה,
ve-akrinu hu ma de-kasiv be-seifer oraissa de-Moshe,
and we had him recite what was written in the... in the
ספר sefer of משה, Moshe, in the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, which
is you know ככה יעשה
לאיש אשר לא יבנה את בית אחיו. kacha ye'aseh la'ish asher asher
lo yivneh es beis achiv. Okay, so or no, excuse me, לא
חפצתי לקחתה. lo chafatzti lekachtah. ככה kacha is what the community says
back. Okay, but he, he says לא חפצתי לקחתה lo chafatzti lekachtah
and so we had him say, we had him say the right...
right verse. Okay, now, so how does that prove anything? Well, since
he says you know
that we said that even though he's coming to do חליצה, chalitzah,
we say to him, if hey buddy, if you want you could
do יבום, yibum, it's obviously יבם יבאם, yabeim yabeim, so you see
that even though we're saying חליצה chalitzah comes first, we still holding
out the option of doing יבום. yibum. So in the middle of
showing demonstrating that we're still holding out the option of doing יבום,
yibum, we have this fascinating description of what the actual event looked
like and how this was written up in the formal court document.
Now we're going to say one thing about this formal court document,
about the phrase in it, אשתמודענא דאיהו. ishtamo dei inahu. So what
does it mean we recognized that he was a paternal brother? So
פליגי רב אחא ורבינא paligi Rav Achai ve-Ravina was a debate of
Rav Achai and Ravina. חד אמר בעדים, chad amar be-eidim, witnesses testified
that he was a paternal brother, וחד אמר אפילו קרוב ואפילו אשה.
ve-chad amar afilu karov ve-afilu isha. No, we can even use a
relative or a woman,
even people like we do by testifying that the husband is dead,
even people that normally are not כשר kosher witnesses, we can use
them to show that this person is a paternal brother and to
do חליצה. chalitzah.
Of course if how do we prove that?
Well, whatever, we know, we saw in the family the, you know,
whatever the way in which people have an awareness of it. It's
like when a rabbi has to write a document, I know that
this person is Jewish, you know? So והלכתא גילוי מילתא בעלמא הוא
ואפילו קרוב ואפילו אשה. ve-hilchasa giluy milsa b'alma hu ve-afilu karov ve-afilu
isha. And the הלכה halacha is this is not real testimony, this
is just something that is revealing stuff that is known to people
anyway. And therefore we can accept even people that normally would not
be good witnesses in a formal sense, a relative or a woman,
presumably even one witness, and therefore we can take whatever evidence we
need to show that this guy is a brother-in-law and can do
חליצה. chalitzah. Of course, the reason for that is why do you
need to have proof? If there's no brother-in-law, then she doesn't need
חליצה. chalitzah. But the point is, it might well be known that
there are brother-in-laws and she does need חליצה, chalitzah, and she's bringing
in front of us some guy that we're not aware of is
the brother-in-law, so you could imagine a little bit of a trick,
right? My other brother, the other brother-in-laws, one guy's planning on doing
יבום yibum or they're refusing to do anything, so she schlepped some
stranger to בית דין Beis Din and claims that he's the brother-in-law.
So that's why there has to be some type of testimony, some
type of establishing that he is the brother-in-law. But the relevance again
for us is even though we said מצות חליצה קודמת, mitzvas chalitzah
kodemes, we have two versions now where the brother-in-law is told you
can yes, you know, do חליצה chalitzah or do יבום, yibum, it's
your choice. Yes, Michael.
I just don't understand what, I don't know why we're getting into
so many ראיות rayos and discussions around this. Let's go back to
basics, but like you know, if I say, you know, I'm not
keeping שבת Shabbos because God rested on the seventh day, I'm just
keeping it because I'm a Jew.
Alright, right, so the reason is, so we're going to see, but
the reason here that לשם מצוה l'shem mitzvah matters is because we're
overriding something that otherwise would be an ערוה ervah of brother's wife,
and what overrides it is the fact that it's done as a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. So even though technically it'll always be
a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum and nobody is questioning that, the
less we have it as sort of the religious value of a,
you know, sort of framed, you know, for the purpose of a
מצוה, mitzvah, the more uncomfortable we feel about the idea that the
מצוה mitzvah of, you know, brother's wife is being overridden. But I
understand, it's a bizarre idea. It's also going to be a little
bit bizarre what constitutes שלא לשם מצוה, shelo l'shem mitzvah, which we'll
see about in a minute.
Just very quickly, that you know it seems over here at least
in the תורה Torah that the whole חליצה chalitzah is almost, you
know, like embarrassing sort of.
Right, yeah, that's true, the גמרא Gemara has completely removed that aspect,
that is true.
We're telling him to go and do that and it seems like,
you know,
right, right, it becomes, right, and that's interesting, you know, that even
the whole reading of it is the court document very much just
made it some technical procedure, there was no sense of shame and
embarrassment, and of course you have to assume that since we're going
to prioritize חליצה, chalitzah, or certainly since we want to hold out
חליצה chalitzah as an option if nobody's willing to do יבום, yibum,
we don't want to make this an embarrassing process,
and that's also maybe why the first version of the document didn't
even mention that he had to say the פסוקים pesukim of לא
חפצתי לקחתה lo chafatzti lekachta because it's the פסוקים pesukim that frame
sort of that sense that
he's shurking his responsibility and so on, so obviously we don't want
to necessarily highlight that aspect. Yes.
Is there significance that the woman is bringing the man to the
court because it's חליצה chalitzah as opposed to where יבום yibum was
the man bringing the woman?
One more time with that?
Is it significant to see that the woman is bringing the man
to the court because it's חליצה? chalitzah?
Yes, because it's חליצה, chalitzah, and if it was יבום, yibum, I
mean he wouldn't bring, but he would be seen as the actor.
Right, he would be seen as the actor. Correct. Okay, now, but
we're not done with this idea whether חליצה chalitzah comes first or
יבום. yibum. So let's continue, four lines down in the middle-sized lines.
בראשונה שהיו מתכוונים לשם מצוה, barishonah shehayu miskavnim l'shem mitzvah, originally when
they would do it for the purpose of מצוה, mitzvah, מצות יבום
קודמת למצות חליצה, mitzvas yibum kodemes l'mitzvas chalitzah, ועכשיו שאין מתכוונים לשם
מצוה אמרו מצות חליצה קודמת למצות יבום. ve-achshav she-ein miskavnim l'shem mitzvah
amru mitzvas chalitzah kodemes l'mitzvas yibum.
So that's the משנה Mishnah that we quoted earlier, okay, that where
it comes first, although we've seen that how much it comes first
is being questioned. So now we're going to look at this. אמר
רמי בר חמא אמר רב יצחק חזרו לומר, amar Rami bar Chama
amar Rav Yitzchak chazru lomar, that was all very nice but then
they went back to the original position and they said מצות יבום
קודמת למצות חליצה, mitzvas yibum kodemes l'mitzvas chalitzah, the מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibum comes first. אמר ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar lei
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said what, איכשר
דרי? achshar daray?
All of a sudden the generations have gotten better? have got like
if the problem was people weren't doing it לשם שמים lishmah shamayim
earlier, you know, which is interesting, right, that sense of ירידת הדורות,
yeridat hadorot, like you know people think like ירידת הדורות yeridat hadorot
is like some some like axiomatic position. Actually, you know, different גמרות
gemarot have different attitudes towards whether we think that later generations are
getting better or worse, but nevertheless there's a skepticism which is sort
of saying: why all of a sudden do things change? What, all
of a sudden you think that the later generations, you know, are
פרמער frummer than the earlier ones? So no, here's why. מעיקרא סברי
לה כאלבא שאול Me'ikara savri lah ke'Abba Shaul because originally they held
like אבא שאול Abba Shaul that says that your כוונה kavanah matters.
ולבסוף סברי לה כרבנן U'levasof savri lah keRabbanan and then they went
back to the רבנן Rabbanan who says your כוונה kavanah doesn't really
matter. דתניא, Detanya, now we're going to see what's at the heart
of this issue.
אבא שאול אומר,
Abba Shaul omer, אבא שאול Abba Shaul says: הכונס את יבמתו לשם
נוי, Hakones et yevamto leshem noi, somebody who marries his sister-in-law for
the purpose of beauty, so desire let's say, לשום אישות leshum ishut
or for the purpose of marriage. Now what's the matter for the
purpose of marriage? So תוספות Tosafot basically says it's like, you know,
you want to have a status in society as being a married
person, okay? ולשום דבר אחר U'leshum davar acher
for any other ulterior motive. We're going to see in the next
משנה mishnah that you inherit your dead brother's estate. So כאילו פוגע
בערוה. Ke'ilu pogea be'ervah. It's as if he is having sex with
a forbidden with a woman who is who is forbidden to him
who is an ערוה, ervah, who's considered a forbidden sexual act. וקרוב
אני בעיני להיות הולד ממזר Vekarov ani be'einai lihyot havlad mamzer and
it's at I would consider it as if the child was a
virtual ממזר. mamzer. Because when it even though technically it is an
act of יבום, yibum, when it's not done for the purpose of
presumably the מצוה, mitzvah, which is either like לשם שמים lishmah shamayim
or להקים שם אחיו, lehakim shem achiv, then the whole you undermining
the whole you know reason that we that the justification for why
it overrides the for why it overrides the prohibition of עריות arayot
and therefore it's as if the עריות arayot issue were still there.
So that's a pretty it's pretty quite fascinating, right? You know, talk
about having not a non-purely technical הלכתית halachic way of looking at
things. Right? You know, here he's looking at it much more in
terms of a certain sense of like religious values. It's not, you
know, a technical consideration. You have this מצוה, mitzvah, it overrides and
so on. No, it's this whole the value of what's being served
here להקים שם אחיו lehakim shem achiv is what is allowing for
this override. And when that's sort of not what's going on, at
least not in people's minds, I mean you could still say who
cares whether it's going on in his mind? If he has a
kid, it's להקים שם אחיו. lehakim shem achiv. But nevertheless maybe if
he's doing it for his purposes, it won't be framed at some
societal level in their own rel- I don't know. So somehow, but
since that is what is justifying it, when that's not there, even
though technically the override is present, he says it completely changes the
act. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, וחכמים vachachamim say: no. יבמה יבוא עליה
מכל מקום. Yevamah yavo aleiha mikol makom. Give me a break. The
תורה Torah says you do the act of sex, that's what's allowed.
End of story. Since when does whether you're doing it לשם שמים
lishmah shamayim change the הלכה halachah or not? So and therefore it
was the reason that we went back to say יבום yibum was
קודם kodem was it was a question of going back to which
position here we think is the one you know is the one
that we go by. Do we really think it's a problem when
it's done שלא לשם שמים? shelo lishmah shamayim? We'll do a little
bit more and then I want to talk about how this actually
played out plays out למעשה. lema'aseh.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאן תנא להא דתנו
רבנן? Man tanna leha detanu rabbanan? Who teaches that which the רבנן
Rabbanan taught? יבמה יבוא עליה מצוה. Yevamah yavo aleiha mitzvah. That's a
מצוה. mitzvah. שבחילה היתה לו בכלל היתר. Shebatchilah hayetah lo bichlal heter.
Originally this woman that's you know his sister-in-law was permitted to him.
נאסרה. Ne'esrah. Then she became
forbidden. וחזרה והותרה. Vechazrah vehutrah. Then she became permitted again. תחזור תחזור
להתירה הראשון? Tachzor tachzor leheteirah harishon? Maybe she goes back to being
as permitted as she originally was? תלמוד לומר יבמה יבוא עליה מצוה.
Talmud lomar yevamah yavo aleiha mitzvah. The brother-in-law shall shall come into
shall have sex with her. That's a מצוה. mitzvah. So what does
this mean? She started מותר, mutar, then אסור, assur, now she's מותר,
mutar, but not as מותר mutar as before. What's going on? So
the גמרא Gemara says: מאן תנא? Man tanna? Who is this תנא?
tanna? אמר יצחק בר אבדימי אבא שאול היא. Amar Yitzchak bar Avdimi
Abba Shaul hi. This is אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. This works with
אבא שאול's Abba Shaul's approach. Why? והכי קאמר, Vehachi ka'amar, here's how
you have to read it. יבמה יבוא עליה מצוה. Yevamah yavo aleiha
mitzvah. שבחילה היתה לו בכלל היתר. Shebatchilah hayetah lo bichlal heter. Originally
this woman, before she got married to her brother-in-law, right? Before she
got married to his brother, this woman was completely מותר mutar to
him. רצה לשום נוי כונסה רצה לשום אישות כונסה. Ratza leshum noi
konsah ratza leshum ishut konsah.
He could have married her for any motivation. So then what happened?
נאסרה. Ne'esrah. She married his brother and then she became an ערוה,
ervah, completely totally forbidden. חזרה והותרה. Chazrah vehutrah. The brother died. Now
she's permissible again. תחזור תחזור להתירה הראשון? Tachzor tachzor leheteirah harishon? Maybe
she's just as permissible as before and the and marriage could be
for any purpose? תלמוד לומר יבמה יבוא עליה. Talmud lomar yevamah yavo
aleiha. Now
he adds one letter. למצוה. Lemitzvah. The brother-in-law shall come into her
for a מצוה. mitzvah. Meaning, so if it's done for the sake
of the מצוה, mitzvah, that's now when it's allowed. Okay. So that's
the position of אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. רבא אמר, Rava amar, he's
being descriptive, it's proscriptive. Right. רבא אמר, Rava amar, אפילו תימא רבנן.
afilu teima Rabbanan. No, I could read that according to the רבנן.
Rabbanan. והכי קאמר, Vehachi ka'amar, and here's how you read it. יבמה
יבוא עליה מצוה. Yevamah yavo aleiha mitzvah. שבחילה היתה לו בכלל היתר.
Shebatchilah hayetah lo bichlal heter. רצה כונסה. Ratza konsah. What was originally
that she was היתר heter before the brother-in-law married before the brother
before the brother married her, if he wanted כונסה, kohnsa, רצה אינו
כונסה. ratza eino kohnsa. This woman was totally, you could do whatever
you wanted, he could choose to marry this woman, he could choose
not to marry this woman. Next, then she becomes forbidden, she marries
his brother, חזרה והותרה, chazra v'hutra, the brother dies, now she's permitted.
יכול תחזור להיתירה הראשון, yachol tachzor l'heteirah harishon,
maybe she's back in the original state of like completely neutral vis-a-vis
him. It's interesting what היתר heter means, not that she's permitted to
him, but like he has no obligation. רצה כונסה רצה
אינו כונסה, ratza kohnsa ratza eino kohnsa, maybe he can choose whether
to marry her or not. So the Gemara says, what do you
mean? Wait, wait, that's not even an הויא אמינא. hava amina. רצה
אינו כונסה? ratza eino kohnsa? אגידא ביה, agida bei, what do you
mean he could choose not to marry her? There's a זיקה, zika,
she's tied to him. It's an interesting phrase. Until now we've been
using the word זיקה, zika, now we use אגידא. agida. She's bound
to him. What do you mean? What? We never would have had
an הויא אמינא hava amina he could walk away. So אגידא ביה
agida bei בכדי תיפוק? bichdi teipok? She should walk away, she should
go out with nothing? אלא אימא רצה כונסה רצה חולץ לה. ela
eima ratza kohnsa ratza choletz la. No, here's how to read it.
Maybe now that
the brother has died, maybe it's equivalent whether he wants to marry
her or whether he wants to do חליצה, chalitza, the same way
it was equivalent before she married the brother. תלמוד לומר יבמה יבוא
עליה מצוה. talmud lomar yevama yavo aleha mitzvah. No,
the primary מצוה mitzvah is to do יבום. yibum. Reading it the
exact opposite of אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, right? When you read it
like אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, it's יבמה יבוא עליה yevama yavo aleha
is only allowed when it's done for the right purposes. This is
being read to say, don't think חליצה chalitza and יבום yibum are
equal options. No, יבום yibum is the primary
option. Okay?
So, alright. So יבמה
יבוא עליה מצוה. yevama yavo aleha mitzvah. אימא סיפא. eima seifa. So
let's take a look though, if that's what you're saying, let's take
a look at how that reads ארישא. areisha. There's a question about
the order of the ברייתא. braita. How that reads in the first
half or second half of this ברייתא, braita, because this is a
larger ברייתא braita and it applies this idea of היתר איסור היתר
heter issur heter to another case. Let's look at the other case.
מצות תאכל במקום קדוש. matzot teiachel b'makom kadosh. You, the כהנים, kohanim,
shall eat, you know, the מנחה mincha as מצות matzot in a
holy
place. Okay? מצוה. mitzvah. שבתחילה היתה בכלל היתר. she-bitchila hayta bichlal heter.
Originally this flour, מצה, matza, was completely permissible before it was sanctified.
You know, you could do whatever you wanted with it. נאסרה, ne'esra,
it becomes forbidden, טפס להו והוקדשה, tfas lahu v'hukdesha, it got sanctified.
וחזרה והותרה. v'chazra v'hutra. Then after the קומץ kometz was brought, it
became now permissible for the כהנים kohanim to eat it again. יכול
תחזור להיתירה הראשון, yachol tachzor l'heteirah harishon, maybe it goes back to
being fully permissible. תלמוד לומר מצות תאכל במקום קדוש מצוה. talmud lomar
matzot teiachel b'makom kadosh mitzvah. You have to eat it in a
holy place, מצוה. mitzvah. Now what does that mean? How do you
read that? How do you parse that? בשלמא לרבא דאמר הא מני
רבנן היא, bishlama l'Rava d'amar ha manni rabanan hi, according to the
רבא Rava that said the issue of חליצה chalitza was explain- יבום
וחליצה yibum v'chalitza worked according to the rabbis and it was saying
like they're not equivalent options. You have to prioritize יבום, yibum, that's
how we read that. הכא
נמי הכי קאמר, hacha nami hachi ka'amar, here's how you read it
parallel about the מצה matza and the מנחה. mincha. מצות תאכל במקום
קדוש מצוה. matzot teiachel b'makom kadosh mitzvah. שבתחילה היתה בכלל היתר. she-bitchila
hayta bichlal heter. רצה אוכלה רצה אינו אוכלה. ratza ochla ratza eino
ochla.
Just like רבא Rava sort of framed his relationship with the woman,
could choose to marry, could choose not to
marry before the יבום yibum occurred. Here too, he could choose to
eat מצה, matza, not eat the מצה, matza, right? There's no obligation
to eat it. Okay? רצה אוכלה, ratza ochla, so נאסרה וחזרה והותרה.
ne'esra v'chazra v'hutra.
Okay, so I'm going to read the parentheses. Okay, it became forbidden,
then it became permissible because it got sanctified. It became permitted again
that the קומץ kometz was brought. יכול תחזור להיתירה הראשון, yachol tachzor
l'heteirah harishon, now maybe he has an equivalent option to choose to
eat it or not eat it? The Gemara says, wait a minute,
what's the הויא אמינא? hava amina? How could he have an equivalent
option? רצה אוכלה רצה אינו אוכלה? ratza ochla ratza eino ochla? So
רצה אינו אוכלה, ratza eino ochla, והכתיב? v'haktiv? I'm sorry, דאכתי לא
אכלה אינו אוכלה? d'achti lo ochla eino ochla?
Maybe, you know, he has an equivalent option to eat or not.
So the Gemara says, what do you mean? רצה אינו אוכלה? ratza
eino ochla? How could you think he has an option not to
eat it? The כהנים. kohanim. והכתיב ואכלו אתם אשר כפר בהם. v'haktiv
v'achlu otam asher kuppar bahem.
They, the כהנים, kohanim, should eat it through which, like, the atonement
is achieved. מלמד שהכהנים אוכלים ובעלים מתכפרים. melamed she-hakohanim ochlim u'be'alim mitchaprin.
The כהנים kohanim eat the מנחה mincha and the owners get atonement.
אלא, ela, so here was the הויא אמינא. hava amina. רצה הוא
אוכלה רצה כהן אחר אוכלה. ratza hu ochla ratza kohen acher ochla.
Maybe he could eat it, maybe somebody else could eat it. It
has to be eaten, but maybe somebody else could eat it. Someone
who did not do the עבודה, avoda, did not bring the קומץ,
kometz, exactly. תלמוד לומר מצות תאכל במקום קדוש מצוה. talmud lomar matzot
teiachel b'makom kadosh mitzvah. It has to be eaten and the repetition,
although the פסוק pasuk doesn't talk about the כהן kohen who brought
it, but the repetition of underscoring it has to be eaten is
telling you there's a מצוה mitzvah דווקא davka with him. So anyway,
structurally it works similar to רבא. Rava. Maybe you could choose to
do it or not do it, that's equivalent to do, let's say,
יבום yibum or חליצה. chalitza. It's equivalent to eat it or to
have somebody else eat it. It tells you, no, there's a prioritizing.
First you יבום yibum rather than do חליצה. chalitza. First you have
to eat it before somebody else can eat it and somewhat parallel
to the options that you had before the whole process began. That's
how it works according to רבא. Rava.
And that's obviously because of the כוונה.
kavanah. Right, so that's the point. So it works according to רבא.
Rava. רבא *Rava*, but now it doesn't work well according to אבא
שאול Abba Shaul, *Abba Shaul*. Okay, so אלא לרבי יצחק בר אבדימי
דאמר אבא שאול Abba Shaul היא *Ela l'Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi d'amar
Abba Shaul hi*, it's אבא שאול Abba Shaul, *Abba Shaul*, הכא מאי
תרי גווני איכא *hacha mai trei gavne ika*? How are there two
variations of the same act? Right, for רבא *Rava*, there could be
two acts. Do you do ייבום *yibum* first or חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*
first? Do you have to eat it or can somebody else eat
it? And we prioritize one. But according to the אבא שאול *Abba
Shaul* read, it's about describing the character of the act. How would
that how here what are the two types of ways you can
eat מצה matzah, *matzah*, the מנחה mincha *mincha*, that one is preferable
to the other? All right, let's take a look. וכי תימא רצה
לתיאבון אכלה רצה אכילה גסה אכלה *V'hachi teima ratza l'tei'avon achlah ratza
achilah gassah achlah*. Maybe you could eat it when you're hungry, maybe
you could eat it when you're full and you're stuffing yourself. So
that's not an option. אכילה גסה מי שמה אכילה *Achilah gassah mi
shma achilah*? Forced eating is not eating. דאמר ריש לקיש האוכל אכילה
גסה ביום הכיפורים פטור *D'amar Resh Lakish ha'ochel achilah gassah b'Yom HaKippurim
patur*. Okay, מלא תעונה *mi lo te'uneh*. If you eat a forced
eating, you're totally stuffed and you're just Of course there's degrees, as
תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* points out, of אכילה גסה *achilah gassah*. One level
of אכילה גסה *achilah gassah* is, "Oh, I can't eat another bite.
Oh, dessert? Okay, fine." So that's not an אכילה גסה *achilah gassah*
that you'd be פטור *patur* for on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. Okay,
but there's another point where you really are have to force yourself
to eat something. Okay, right. That anyway there's a level of אכילה
גסה *achilah gassah*. פטור מלא תעונה *Patur mi lo te'uneh*, you have
not violated undoing your affliction because it actually is not giving you
any satisfaction, which is interesting because you could say that the יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur* idea, maybe not a general idea by אכילה *achilah*.
Anyway, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says there is it would not be
a possibility that you could eat it אכילה גסה *achilah gassah*. The
funny thing is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* didn't have to do an
אכילה גסה *achilah gassah* to that level. It could have said maybe
it's eat it hungry or eat it when you're not so hungry
and prioritize eating it when you're hungry. For whatever reason, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* doesn't go there although that seems like a reasonable option.
אלא רצה מצה matzah אכלה רצה חמץ chametz אכלה *Ela ratza matzah
achlah ratza chametz achlah*. Maybe you could eat it מצה *matzah*, maybe
you could eat it as חמץ chametz *chametz*, maybe the rest of
it you can eat even if it's חמץ *chametz* because it's not
the part that's offered on the מזבח *mizbeach*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, "Wait one minute, that's not even a that's not possible."
והא כתיב *V'ha k'tiv*, remember,
both variations are acceptable, we're just prioritizing. So either prioritizing ייבום *yibum*
over חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*, this כהן kohen. *kohen* over another כהן kohein.
*kohen*, doing it לשם שמים leshem shamayim *l'shem shamayim* over not doing
it לשם שמים leshem shamayim, *l'shem shamayim*. But if it was about
חמץ *chametz* versus מצה *matzah*, that's not about prioritizing. Eating it חמץ
*chametz* is not an option. והא כתיב לא lo, תאפה חמץ חלקם
*V'ha k'tiv lo te'afeh chametz chelkam*. They cannot make חמץ *chametz* and
then the next פסוק *pasuk* is חלקם נתתי להם מאשי *chelkam natati
lahem mei'ishai*, I have given them their portion, but it's read as
they cannot even allow their portion to become חמץ *chametz*. דאמר ריש
לקיש אפילו חלקם לא תאפה חמץ *D'amar Resh Lakish afilu chelkam lo
te'afeh chametz*. Okay, so therefore, what's again, what are the two variations
with both will work but one is being prioritized and they're variations
of the same act? אלא רצה מצה אכלה רצה חלוט אכלה *Ela
ratza matzah achlah ratza chalut achlah*. You would maybe I can eat
it as מצה *matzah*, maybe I can eat it that I didn't
sort of just normally bake the grain, I scalded it first, I
did חליטה *chalitah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, "One minute, חלוט
היכי דמי *chalut heichi dami*? What's the case of doing חליטה *chalitah*
scalding of the of the flour or of the grain? אם מצה
היא המצה היא *Im matzah hi hamatzah hi*. If when you go
through that process and then and then you bake it, it's still
considered מצה *matzah*, המצה היא *hamatzah hi*. So it's מצה *matzah*, so
why would it be a second-level priority? ואי לא vi'lo, מצה היא
*V'ei lo matzah hi*, if that would not be considered מצה *matzah*,
if that becomes חמץ *chametz* or something else,
so ואי לא מצה היא מצות אמר רחמנא amar rachmana. *v'ei lo
matzah hi matzot amar rachmana*. So then you're not יוצא *yotzei*. So
again, where's the scenario where it's okay but a but a second-level
option? So לא לעולם אימא לך מצה היא *lo l'olam
eima lach matzah hi*. It is מצה *matzah*. ולהכי תנא tana ביה
קרא מצות יאכל *u'l'hachi tana bei kra matzot ye'achel* to tell you
that there are two grades of מצה *matzah*. There's pure מצה *matzah*
and there's, "All right, fine, it's מצה *matzah* but it's not really
it's not ideal מצה *matzah*." So that's what the two variations are.
So similar to the ייבום *yibum*, there's ייבום לשם שמים *yibum l'shem
shamayim* and ייבום שלא לשם שמים *yibum shelo l'shem shamayim*. Here, there's
something which is classic מצה *matzah* and something which is בדיעבד *b'di'eved*
considered מצה *matzah*. Okay, I'm not going to go into the details
of what exactly you're doing to the flour and variations and so
on. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* starts getting into it, it's a discussion for
another time. Okay, דקתני *d'katani*.
So now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, "אלא חלוט מצה היא דקאמינא
למאי הלכתא *Ela chalut matzah hi d'kamina l'mai hilchata*? So if you
say it's מצה *matzah* but you're saying that it's not ideal, for
what purpose is it מצה *matzah*? Now that's a bizarre question because
the first purpose is that בדיעבד *b'di'eved* you are יוצא *yotzei*. Right,
the whole point here was to prioritize but to say the other
option still can work. So the first thing it should be that
בדיעבד *b'di'eved* you're יוצא *yotzei*. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gives you
another option. It says למאי הלכתא *l'mai hilchata*? לומר שיוצא בו ידי
חובתו בפסח *L'omar she'yotzei bo y'dei chovato b'Pesach*. You can use it
for פסח *Pesach*. Maybe by מנחה mincha *mincha* it's prioritized, but by
other places you need מצה *matzah*, it's not prioritized I mean, maybe
by מנחה *mincha* it's second degree, but by other places it's not
second degree. Okay, אף על פי דחליטה מעיקרא *Af al pi d'chalitah
mei'ikara*, even if you scalded the grain initially, כיון דהדר אפייה *keivan
d'hadar afyeih*, since afterwards you went ahead... you cooked it בתנור, לחם
עוני קרינא ביה, lechem oni karina bei, we call it poor person's
bread, ואדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו בפסח. ve-adam yotzei bo yedai chovato
be-Pesach. So it's similar in structure to the idea that there's a
priority and a second degree. So what we have here is מר
Mar starts by saying things reverse, חליצה chalitza was more important, then
immediately says, yeah, but even if חליצה chalitza is more important, we
sort of hold both options, and then it says, and actually later
they went back and they actually said יבום yibum was more important
because they wound up ruling like the רבנן. Rabbanan. So the whole
end of the גמרא Gemara after introducing this one line that they
prioritized חליצה chalitza is, yeah, but now basically חליצה chalitza is no
more important, if anything we're back to where we used to be,
that יבום yibum is more important. And that seems to be the
conclusion of the בבלי. Bavli. The conclusion of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is
like the original, like you know, the משנה, Mishna, the גמרא Gemara
started with, which is חליצה chalitza? is more important. And any guesses
why this might be? I sort of told you this a few
weeks ago. Because בבל Bavel was a polygamous society, it was,
and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was a monogamous society. ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael was under the influence of Rome and Rome was basically becoming
monogamous and certainly
then monogamous but licentious, and then that was followed by Christianity, you
know, in Christian lands, which was monogamous, whereas בבל Bavel was Zoroastrianism,
which was polygamous, and then followed by Islam, which was polygamous. So
בבל, Bavel, if you have polygamy, doing יבום yibum is not such
a big problem, right? There's no issue basically, it's okay if you're
already married. If you're in a monogamous society, then we can't be
prioritizing יבום yibum because even though there'll be scenarios where that will
work, we have to basically at a societal level create a prioritizing
of חליצה chalitza because יבום yibum is very often not an option
and we don't want to hold it out as an ideal in
a society in which you do not have more than one wife.
So not surprisingly, guess what? This maps to the ראשונים Rishonim and
to אשכנז Ashkenaz and ספרד. Sefarad. And ספרד Sefarad therefore that are
the inheritors of the בבל Bavel culture and also of Islamic lands
basically continue to hold that מצות יבום קודמת. mitzvah yibum kodemet.
And I don't know, but I think that this, I mean, now
of course even in ספרדי Sephardi lands or whatever, you know, we
have monogamy, but I still think that in some societies until very
recently יבום yibum was seen as of course the first option, whereas
in אשכנזי Ashkenazi lands which, you know, in Christian lands and so
on where it was monogamy and חרם דרבנו גרשום Cherem de-Rabbeinu Gershom
and all that, it's clear that מצות חליצה קודמת. mitzvah chalitza kodemet.
So while רש״י, Rashi, you know, just interprets the גמרא Gemara simply,
and if you just read רש״י Rashi you wouldn't have any sense
that that wasn't the הלכה halacha that we should, you know, the
way the גמרא Gemara here seems to end, which is sort of
going back to יבום, yibum, let's take a very quick look at
תוספות. Tosafos So תוספות says, אמר רב אין כופין. Amar Rav ein
kofin. So he says,
I'm going to tell you, he says,
right.
Let me find it.
Wait
a minute.
Okay, so let's just, I'll just skip to the following like וכי
חברו. ve-chi havru. Do you see the line that starts with that?
It's about fifteen lines down, it's the beginning of the line וכי
חברו. ve-chi havru. It's like three lines below where the עין משפט
Ein Mishpat ends on the far right. Okay, so he deals with
the case of the גמרא Gemara that seems like it was an
equivalent option. What are you going to do if you really want
to say that it's not equivalent, you have to do חליצה? chalitza.
So let's see how he reads that גמרא. Gemara וכי חברו אתו
לקמיה דרב, ve-chi havru atu l'kamei de-Rav, אותן שהיו מתכוונים לשם מצוה.
otan she-hayu mitkavnim le-shem mitzvah.
These were people that were coming to רב Rav for the sake
of the מצוה. mitzvah. Then he said, oh, you're already coming for
the sake of a מצוה, mitzvah, you could do יבום. yibum. ורב
יהודה נמי דאסיקני צבית יבומי. ve-Rav Yehuda nami de-assikni tzavit yibumei. That's
brilliant. He says that the document where the guy's doing חליצה chalitza,
and in the document it said that we told him, oh, if
you want you could do יבום, yibum, ודאסיקני צבית יבומי ve-d'assikni tzavit
yibumei באותן שבאו לפנינו לחלוץ. be-otan she-bau l'faneinu lachlot.
They would only, you know the only person who was given the
option to do יבום? yibum? The person that anyway was coming to
do חליצה. chalitza. Because since he was coming to do חליצה, chalitza,
clearly he doesn't have any ulterior motives to do יבום. yibum. Okay,
so it's like the perfect Catch-22. Oh, you want to do יבום?
yibum? No, you're not allowed to do יבום yibum because clearly you
might have ulterior motives. Oh, you don't want to do יבום? yibum?
Okay, in that case יבום yibum is an option. Oh, so you
changed your mind? Oh, then you're not allowed to do יבום. yibum.
Okay, so שאותן אם היו מיבמים היו מתכוונים לשם מצוה שהרי היו
מתכוונים לשם חליצה. she-otan im hayu meyabmim hayu mitkavnim le-shem mitzvah she-harei
hayu mitkavnim le-shem chalitza.
They were coming to do חליצה. chalitza. So since they were coming
to do חליצה, chalitza for them יבום yibum was allowed. But if
you were coming to do יבום, yibum, then יבום yibum wouldn't be
allowed. שלא יחשימו יבום באחוות. she-lo yechasheim yibum le-achva'at. אבל אחריני אין
מניחים ליבם. aval achrini ein manichim le-yabem. Others we don't allow, אלא
אדרבא כופין לחלוץ. ella adaraba kofin lachlot. Or we. Force חליצה. chalitza,
ואמר רבינו תם דהלכה כאבא שאול כסתם מתניתין דבכורות ve’amar Rabbeinu Tam
de’halacha ke’Abba Shaul kestam matnitin de’bechoros דלא כרמי בר חמא delo ke’Rami
Bar Chama דאמר חזרו לומר דמצות יבום קודמת כרבנן de’amar chazaru lomar
demitzvas yibum kodemes kerabbanan etc.
etc.
Okay, and then at the very end, either the last line he
says, and the ר"ח Rach פסק
כאן pasak kan right before the words דמתחזיא, demitchazya, דמצות יבום קודמת,
demitzvas yibum kodemes, so first רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says מצות יבום
קודמת mitzvas yibum kodemes וחזר בו vechazar bo דודאי devakei מצות חליצה
פסק דמצות חליצה קודמת. mitzvas chalitza pasak demitzvas chalitza kodemes. So there's
this fascinating debate, it's a מחלוקת בבלי ירושלמי אשכנזים ספרדים machlokes Bavli
Yerushalmi Ashkenazim Sefardim and תוספות here tries to read the בבלי Bavli
according to the אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach that מצות חליצה mitzvas chalitza comes
first. Okay, some quick questions and then move on. Michael's been dying
to ask for a while.
What I didn't say for the אבא שאול, I don't understand why
we didn't say, "Okay, I want to eat the מנחה because
the same מצוה" mitzvah or "if I want I can eat the
מנחה" because there's no basis in any other area. The only reason
the לשם שמים אבא שאול does not generally say that, "Oh, if
it's not לשם שמים, it's a completely סוג ב׳ sug beis type
of an act." It's only in the case of יבום וחליצה yibum
vechalitza where it's overriding an איסור ערוה. issur ervah. That was what
bothered אבא שאול, it's not a general issue. Yes, David?
It's interesting they're using the example of מצה, which is like, you
know, it's opposite to חמץ in terms of, like, lack of the
desire and the יצר הרע. yetzer hara. Oh, that's nice point, right.
And it's also true that the מצה and חמץ are the exact
same ingredients. A lot of it has to do with how you
approach it and how you sort of, right, that's nice, very nice,
yes.
When he says אגידא ביה, agida bei, like you said it was
זיקה, zika, is that the same language as like אגודה אחת? aguda
achas? Tied, connected, tied
to.
They're still bound.
Okay, next משנה. mishnah. מ״א ע״א. Mem Amud Aleph. All right, let's
get a move on. Anyway, that was very, you know, that could
have been like the very first סוגיא sugya of this מסכת. maseches.
החולץ ליבמתו. hacholetz liyvimto.
If somebody does חליצה chalitza, to his sister-in-law, הרי הוא כאחד מן
האחים לנחלה. harei hu ke'echad min ha'achim linachal. He still gets an
equivalent portion of the estate. Maybe you'll say, "Look, you did חליצה,
chalitza you completely—" meaning the brother's estate. Who's now—if nobody does יבום,
yibum, then the other brothers equally divide the brother's estate. Well, maybe
we should say, "Well, the guy who did חליצה, chalitza he basically
showed that he was rejecting everything from the brother." You know, it's
sort of like the whole story by Ruth, right? And then he
says to the גואל, goel, he says, "Oh, you want to get
the land? You get Ruth in the package." "Okay, then I change
my mind." So here it's like the reverse, right? So if you're
rejecting the sister-in-law, maybe you're rejecting the estate. No, you get an
equal portion in the estate. And women? No, no, woman never inherit.
ואם יש שם אב, ve'im yesh sham av, however, if there's the
father is still alive, נכסים של אב, nichasim shel av, the father
inherits the brother, okay, when חליצה chalitza is done. Okay, when חליצה
chalitza, is done, right, when יבום yibum is done it's a different
discussion. הכונס את יבמתו, hakones es yevamto, now somebody who did יבום
yibum זכה בנכסי של אחיו. zacha benichasim shel achiv.
Talk about possible ulterior motives. If you did יבום, yibum, the guy
who does יבום, yibum, he gets all of the dead brother's estate.
רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda omer: בין כך ובין כך bein kach
uvein kach אם יש שם אב נכסים של אב. im yesh sham
av nichasim shel av. This is fascinating. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
יקום על שם אחיו yakum al shem achiv
might—does not mean you get the brother's estate. It's not about property.
Whatever it means in terms of some metaphysical way in which the
son goes after the dead father, but no, that the גמרא Gemara
explicitly rejects the idea of naming—that you have to name after—but it
does not have anything to do with property. And if there's a
father, the father gets the property. Now, if there's no father, would
he say in that case
the brother
gets—well, if there's no father, there's two options: in that case the
guy who did יבום yibum could get it all or in that
case they could divide it. He could be completely rejecting any idea
of property or maybe he's only rejecting it in the presence of
a prior heir of the father. Let's take a look.
What if they have children? If they do a יבום, yibum, they
have children, aren't those children heirs to the deceased man's property?
Only that only if the brother-in-law first got it. But if the
basic הלכה halacha is that you divide the estate or the father
gets it, then the answer would be no. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says פשיטא, peshita, obviously,
obviously... Michael, before you leave, I need you to respond to the
email about coverage for next week if you could look at that,
okay? We basically need Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, so any of those days
you could do. Okay, פשיטא, peshita, גמרא Gemara says like this: פשיטא,
peshita, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, חליצה במקום יבום קיימא. chalitza
bimkom yibum ka'ima.
Obviously the brother who does חליצה chalitza gets an equivalent amount of
the estate. No, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, I might have
thought חליצה במקום יבום קיימא, chalitza bimkom yibum ka'ima, that maybe יבום
yibum is just like חליצה, chalitza ונשקול כולהו נכסי, venishkol kulhu nichasei,
and maybe the same way if you do יבום yibum you get
all the estate, maybe if you do חליצה chalitzah, you get the
whole estate. Okay, and therefore the משנה mishnah is saying is that
not that you don't get less, but that you don't get more.
So the גמרא Gemara says "Wait a minute, if that's what the
משנה mishnah is saying, קא משמע לן, kamashma lan, אי הכי, ee
hachi, הרי הוא כאחד מן האחים, harei hu ke'echad min ha'achim, the
משנה mishnah shouldn't say 'you get as much as one of the
brothers,' it should have said אינו אלא כאחד מן האחים, eino ela
ke'echad min ha'achim, that you don't get any more than one of
the brothers." So obviously we never had a הוה אמינא hava amina
that if you do חליצה chalitzah, you get it all. So מיבעיא
ליה? mibaya lei? אלא הכא, ela hacha, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach
amina, here's what we would have thought. We would have thought הואיל
ואפסדה
מיבום, hoil ve'afsidah miyibum, since you... The one that made this woman
invalid for יבום yibum since you did חליצה, chalitzah. now the other
brothers can't do יבום. yibum. Maybe another brother would have wanted to
do יבום. yibum. So since you went ahead and you made יבום
yibum impossible, לקנסיה? lekansye? Maybe we should fine you and say you
don't get a part of the estate? קמשמע לן kamashma lan that
we don't. So it wanted to make it a rabbinic idea. As
I said, one could have imagined that there would even be a
הוה אמינא havah aminah at the biblical level, that maybe if you're
rejecting her, you're rejecting the estate. Anyway, אם יש שם אב, im
yesh sham av, now if there's a brother, there's a father, excuse
me, when there is in the case of חליצה, chalitzah then the
father inherits. דאמר מר, de'amar mar, אב קודם לכל יוצאי יריכו. av
kodem lechol yotzei yerecho. Then it's a normal הלכה halachah of inheritance,
and the normal הלכה halachah of inheritance is that a son died,
if a person dies and doesn't leave a son, you first go
to the father before you go to the father's children, before you
go to the brothers. Now let's say it's יבום. yibum. הכונס את
יבמתו, hakones et yevamto, the guy did יבום. yibum. So then he
gets the estate. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? יקום על שם אחיו yakum
al shem achiv אמר רחמנא. amar rachmana, He should, he will stand
up on the name of his brother. So the name, like we,
you know, just discussed before by בנות צלפחד, Benot Tzelofchad, right? למה
יגרע שם אבינו. lamah yigara shem avinu.
So the name has to do with the inheritance. אמר רחמנא, והרי
קם. ve'harei kam. So since he was the one that now stood
on his brother's name, that means that he now, the inheritance follows
him. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
even if, if there's a father, it goes to the father, even
if he did יבום. yibum. So אמר עולא, amar Ulla, הלכה כרבי
יהודה. halachah k'Rabbi Yehuda. We rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which
is pretty amazing. וכן אמר רבי יצחק נפחא הלכה כרבי יהודה. vechen
amar Rabbi Yitzchak Napcha halachah k'Rabbi Yehuda. We'll see if we end
this way. ואמר עולא ואיתימא רבי יצחק נפחא, ve'amar Ulla ve'iteima Rabbi
Yitzchak Napcha, מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Yehuda? What's the
reason of רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? דכתיב, dechtiv,
the verse says, והיה הבכור אשר תלד, vehayah habechor asher teled,
and it will be that the first son that will be given
birth will stand up on his, on the father's name. But remember,
you might remember the גמרא Gemara earlier read the verse והיה הבכור
vehayah habechor not about the offspring of the union, but about actually
the brother-in-law doing the act of יבום. yibum. From there it learned
the idea that you go by the oldest son first because it
says והיה הבכור. vehayah habechor. So this והיה הבכור vehayah habechor is
being read to refer to the brother-in-law doing the act of יבום.
yibum. It says כבכור, k'bechor, he's like a firstborn son. Now a
firstborn son normally gets a double portion. That's all very nice, but
there's another הלכה halachah of a firstborn son: מה בכור אין לו
בחיי אב, mah bechor ayn lo bechayei av, but a firstborn son
doesn't get anything if the father's alive, אף האי נמי אין לו
בחיי אב. af hai nami ayn lo bechayei av. Here too, if
the father's alive, he doesn't get anything. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
seems to be saying, if there's no father, I concede the point,
obviously I'm not completely denying that the brother-in-law gets the estate. But
that's if it's a question of which of the brothers are going
to get it. Which of the brothers are going to get it,
you're the guy that did יבום, yibum, you're like a בכור, bechor,
you get this extra portion. But that's if there are only brothers.
If there's a father, it goes to the father. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אי מה בכור, ei mah bechor, but
let's say this, בכור נוטל פי שנים לאחר מיתת אב. bechor notel
pi shenayim le'achar mitat av. Okay, but once the father dies, then
the בכור bechor does get his double portion. אף האי נוטל פי
שנים לאחר מיתת אב? af hai notel pi shenayim le'achar mitat av?
So maybe here too, father's alive, the dead brother's estate goes to
the father. Father dies, now maybe the יבם yabam should be getting
it, now he gets his double portion? So the גמרא Gemara says,
no. מידי יקום על שם אביו כתיב? midi yakum al shem aviv
ktiv? Does the verse say that he replaces his father? No. יקום
על שם אחיו כתיב. yakum al shem achiv ktiv. It says he
replaces his brother, ולא על שם אביו. velo al shem aviv. So
since when his brother died he did not take over the estate,
then he will no longer take over the estate afterwards. Okay? So
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says if there's no father, yes, he gets
a double portion, he takes over his brother's estate, יקום על שם
אחיו. yakum al shem achiv. But if there is a father, it
goes to the father, he is not יקום על שם אחיו yakum
al shem achiv and then he's out for, you know, he's out
from that time on.
How does the act of יבום yibum then מקיים שמו mekayem shemo
at all?
Right, so it's not about property. Look, the simple sense of the
verse I would say is not about property. You know, the רמב"ן
Ramban says it's about something more metaphysical, you know, maybe about גלגול
נשמות gilgul neshamot is what the רמב"ן Ramban sort of alludes to.
But whatever you understand, taking care of
the wife, taking
care of the wife, right? Giving her a home, exactly. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אימא היכא דליכא אב דלישקול
נחלה, eima heicha delika av delishkol nachalah, let's say היכא, heicha, let's
say היכא דליכא אב, heicha delika av,
as long as we're linking, as long as we are for רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda not always having the estate go to the brother,
maybe it should be a bundle package, again, sort of like the
whole story with Ruth and Boaz. So let's say if there's no
father and he's going to get the estate, that's when there's a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, that's when it's יקום על שם אחיו.
yakum al shem achiv. היכא דאיכא אב, heicha de'ika av,
if there is a father, דלא שקיל נחלה, delo shakil nachalah,
that he won't get the estate, לא תתקיים מצות יבום, lo titkayem
mitzvat yibum, maybe then he doesn't have to do יבום? yibum? Maybe
there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum in that case because there's
no נחלה? nachalah? So the גמרא says, מידי יבום בנחלה תלה רחמנא?
midi yibum benachalah talah rachmana? One minute, you think יבום yibum depends
on the estate? Now of course here it's rhetorically. You might remember
that earlier the גמרא said it as a statement: יבום בנחלה תלה
רחמנא. yibum benachalah talah rachmana. יבום yibum goes,
but the גמרא means... Yes, they come, yes, they come together, but
you got the order wrong. You got the causality wrong. It's not
like you need the estate in order for there to be יבום.
yibum. Okay? So יבומי מיקני, yibumey miyatney, יבום yibum is the one
that you start with, you do יבום, yibum, and then that's how
they get bundled. ואיכא נחלה שקלי, vi'ika nachalah shaklei, if there is
a נחלה, nachalah, either the guy actually has property and there's no
father, then you take it. ואי לא, if there's no נחלה, nachalah,
no inheritance because he had no property or because the father's alive,
לא שקלי, lo shaklei, you don't take it. So you are right
that יבום yibum and נחלה nachalah sort of go together, but not
that נחלה nachalah would determine יבום. yibum. It's that יבום yibum determines
נחלה. nachalah. And that's only if, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
there's no father. But it is interesting that, and what's bothering the
גמרא is that this is not normally how we understand it. We
normally do understand it as more tightly
bound, and that whenever there's יבום, yibum, there's נחלה. nachalah. And רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is allowing for the possibility of יבום yibum without
נחלה. nachalah. So the גמרא is not done. Okay? Because until because
we just the only thing we said so far is the הלכה
halacha is like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So the גמרא says like
this: יתיב רב חנינא קרא, yasiv Rav Chanina Kara, רב חנינא Rav
Chanina the like reader, the Torah reader, sat, קמיה דרבי ינאי, kamei
d'Rabbi Yannai, or you know maybe he taught kids how to read
Torah. He sat in front of רבי ינאי. Rabbi Yannai. ויתיב וקאמר,
v'yasiv v'ka'amar, and he was sitting and saying over, הלכה כרבי יהודה.
halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. We read like we were like רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, which is what we've been saying until now. אמר ליה, amar
lei, so רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai said to him, פוק קרי קריך
לברא. puk kari karich l'bara. Go teach your פסוקים psukim outside. Okay,
now that's interesting. Normally we say a תנא tana, sat in front,
and then he says, you know, פוק תני לברא, puk tani l'bara,
teach the ברייתא braisa outside. But he wasn't saying a ברייתא, braisa,
but he was just saying, you know, whatever teachy you have to
teach, get out of the בית מדרש. beis medrash. Okay, אין הלכה
כרבי יהודה תני. ain halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda tani. So the version of
the tradition is אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. ain halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. Not
הלכה כרבי יהודה, halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda, but אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. ain
halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. We don't rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay,
אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. ain halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. I'm sorry, not תני,
tani, אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. ain halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. תני תנא קמיה
דרב נחמן. tani tana kamei d'Rav Nachman. Now a תנא, not somebody
who teaches over tannaitic statements rather than somebody who teaches פסוקים, psukim,
was sitting in front of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, and he said,
and he taught אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. ain halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. Good,
הלכה halacha is not like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. אמר ליה, amar
lei, אלא כמאן? ella k'man? So who is it like? רבנן? Rabbanan?
פשיטא. pshitah. I wouldn't need a ברייתא braisa to tell me we
don't rule like a דעת יחיד. daas yachid. Of course we rule,
of course that should be the default assumption. יחיד ורבים הלכה כרבים.
yachid v'rabbim halacha k'rabbim. So there's no need to have a teach
saying that we reject רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Don't say anything and
it's implicit. So אמר ליה amar lei he said to him, אסמיה?
asamya? So should I sort of cross it out? Should I remove
it from the tradition, this teaching, because it's not necessary? אמר ליה
amar lei לא, no. Here's what happened. Here's how you got this
teaching. את, at, you, when you were taught it, הלכה אסנייך. halacha
asnyach. It was originally taught it, the person who taught it to
you taught you to
say הלכה כרבי יהודה, halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda, not אין הלכה, ain halacha,
הלכה כרבי יהודה. halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. Whoever was at that was a
tradition that we rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. ומקשי הוא דאקילך,
u'mukeshu hu d'akilach,
but you were bothered by this. Why should how do we rule
like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he's a דעת יחיד. daas yachid. ואפכית,
v'afachit, and you intuitively changed the text. You intuitively remembered it as
אין הלכה כרבי יהודה ain halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda because it didn't make
any sense to you to say הלכה כרבי יהודה. halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda.
Okay, so he's reconstructing what must have happened. Clearly this is a
corruption that grew into your original teaching. The original teaching was הלכה,
halacha, but the reason corruptions come up is because you unconsciously fixed
a problematic text. So you unconsciously fixed it. So ולמאי דאפכית שפיר
אפכית. u'limai d'afachit shappir afachit. But you know what? Your fixing was
a correct fixing, because the tradition of הלכה כרבי יהודה halacha k'Rabbi
Yehuda is not the right tradition. So you wound up correcting the
text. So now it's correct according to הלכה. halacha. It's just not
correct as what the original text was. But it's correct according to
הלכה halacha and therefore we should preserve it. Okay, so basically the
גמרא in the end does not is not able to to be
okay with רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, has to understand that נחלה nachalah
always goes together right with with the act of יבום. yibum.
אסמיה asamya is the לשון סומא? loshon suma? No. No, make blinded
and like blot it out?
Yeah, I'm not sure if it's the exact same root, but yes,
should I blot it out, exactly.
Oh, I won't see it anymore. Right. Do we actually פסקן posken
that way?
We פסקן posken אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. ain halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. Yeah.
Okay. So okay.
Now let's see the next משנה. mishnah. החולץ ליבמתו. hachalotz l'yevamto. Somebody
who does חליצה. chalitzah הוא אסור בקרובותיה והיא אסורה בקרוביו. hu assur
bi'krovoteha v'hi assurah bi'krovov. We've quoted this before. Okay. Once חליצה chalitzah
is done, the brother who did חליצה chalitzah. is the woman is
called a חלוצה. chaluza. She's forbidden to a כהן. She has a
גרושה grushah type of a status. One of the other implications of
a גרושה grushah status is if we see her as a גרושה,
grushah, then we see her relationship to the guy who did חליצה
chalitzah as a past husband. So if they're looked at as past
wife and husband, if that's sort of the virtual way they're looked
at, then they can't marry one another's relatives. Because when any relatives
that are אסור assur because of husband and wife remain אסור assur
even after divorce. The only one that changes is wife's sister, and
that's only when the wife dies. But other than that, even after
divorce, all prohibited relatives based on marriage continue after divorce. So now
we're going to look at them as a divorced couple. And therefore
the implications will be all the relatives will be forbidden. It does
not apply to the other brothers, because the other brothers although now,
and it does not apply to the צרה, tzara, to the co-wife,
although now everybody is free from any obligation, this status only applies
to the people that did the actual act, the man that did
it, the brother that did it with the wife. If there's another
wife or other brothers, they're not in the equation. Okay. הוא אסור
באמה ובאם אמה ובאם אביה. Hu assur beimo uveem imo uveem aviha.
He's forbidden with her mother, that would be like wife's mother, and
the grandmother, whether the maternal or paternal grandmother, because that's a, you
know, you can't have sex with a woman and her and her
granddaughter, right? אשה, Isha, you know, בתה בת בתה bitah bat bitah
and so on, so here it would be, you know, the wife's
grandmother, and same in the reverse direction.
ובבתה, uvevitah, the daughter, that's a woman and her daughter, ובבת בתה
ובבת בנה uvevat bitah uvevat binah and her granddaughter. Okay, so that's
he's forbidden in those relations. ובאחותה, uveachotah, and wife's sister, בזמן שהיא
קיימת. bizman shehi kayyamet. The sister is only as long as the
חלוצה chalutzah is still alive. והאחים מותרים, vehachimm mutarin, but his brothers
can marry all these women. Okay. והיא, vehi, now she is אסורה
באביו ובאבי אביו, assurah beaviv uveavi aviv, in his father and his
grandfather. Now that's not obvious that it's parallel because remember all עריות
arayos are defined from the perspective of the man. So what would
be the story about אביו? aviv? So this guy's father, so what
type of what's the relationship? You look at it from the man's
perspective. The relationship is his daughter-in-law. So that is אסור assur in
the Torah. Okay, daughter-in-law is אסור. assur. But how about grandfather? Grandfather,
this is his son's daughter-in-law. So that's not a biblical prohibition. It's
only a rabbinic prohibition. So being included in this Mishnah therefore also
the rabbinic prohibitions. Okay, is that clear how the grandfather is the
son's daughter-in-law? That's only rabbinic.
But wait, grand daughter-in-law.
Granddaughter-in-law. Okay. ובבנו, bivno, the son. Now why is it אסור assur
in the son? Well, the son would be his father's, looking at
it from the son's perspective, father's wife or ex-wife. Okay, that's prohibited.
ובבן בנו, uveven beno, grandson. Now what's grandson? Grandson is grandfather's wife.
Again, that's only rabbinic. So we're including in this rabbinic prohibition.
ובבן אחיו, uveven achiv, brother, because then it's brother's wife. ובבן אחיו,
uveven achiv, brother's son. So brother's son would be, what is that
from the perspective of the son? Father's brother's wife. Okay, that's aunt,
right? Okay, so that's
prohibited. Okay. מותר אדם בקרובת צרת חלוצתו ואסור בצרת קרובת חלוצתו.
mutar adam bikrovat tzarat
chalutzato veassur betzarat krovat chalutzato. That's like a great little riddle. Okay,
so מותר אדם בקרובת צרת חלוצתו mutar adam bikrovat tzarat chalutzato means
the following: קרובת צרת חלוצתו. krovat tzarat chalutzato. Yeah, that's
what? קרובת צרת חלוצתו krovat tzarat chalutzato means, okay, so here's ראובן,
Reuven, okay, married to רחל. Rachel. Okay, here's שמעון, Shimon, who does,
ראובן Reuven dies, שמעון Shimon does חליצה. chalitzah, Okay, now here you've
got ברוך Baruch and ברוך Baruch is married to לאה, Leah, a
sister, and to דבורה. Devorah. Okay. Now, so רחל Rachel is חלוצתו.
chalutzato. Okay, I'm sorry, no, I went already to the second case,
let's get rid of ברוך Baruch in a minute. Okay.
You have רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, and לאה Leah and לאה's
Leah mother, okay, and לאה's Leah daughter,
דינה. Dinah.
Okay. So he does חליצה chalitzah. to רחל. Rachel. רחל Rachel is
חלוצתו. chalutzato. שמעון, Shimon, שמעון, Shimon, he cannot have, you know, he
is forbidden on all of רחל's Rachel relatives. Okay. לאה, Leah, however,
although she's been freed due to the act of חליצה, chalitzah she
is not a חלוצה. chalutzah. She can go ahead and marry a
כהן. She didn't undergo the act of חליצה. chalitzah Therefore she's not
seen as שמעון's Shimon ex-wife. Therefore שמעון Shimon is permitted to marry
relatives—no, she can't because she's brother's wife, right? But שמעון Shimon can
marry relatives of לאה Leah because לאה Leah is not seen as
his ex-wife. So מותר אדם בצרת, mutar adam betzarat, right? This is
the צרה tzara of רחל. Rachel. So he is מותר בקרובה, mutar
bikrovah, the קרוב, karov, דינה, Dinah, the relative of the צרה tzara
of the woman he did חליצה chalitzah to. קרובת צרת חלוצתו. krovat
tzarat chalutzato. That's okay because she doesn't have a status of ex-wife
to him. But what he's not allowed in is, and this is
bizarre why this should be a problem and we'll discuss it tomorrow,
the case I gave you before. ברוך Baruch here is married to
לאה Leah and
דבורה—not Devorah דינה, Dinah, and דבורה. Devorah. Guess who he can't marry
in this case? Like why should he be אסור assur in anybody,
right? I mean, he can't marry לאה. Leah. Why can't he marry
לאה Leah in this case? Because לאה, Leah, לאה, Leah,
ברוך Baruch has no relationship to these guys. But לאה Leah is
רחל's Rachel sister. Okay. So why can't he marry לאה? Leah? Because
לאה Leah is his ex-wife as it were, his חלוצה's chalutzah sister.
Which doesn't have any
implication...
צרת, tzaras, דבורה Dvorah is the צרה, tzarah, the co-wife of, צרת,
tzaras, קרובה, krovah, the relative of חליצתו, chalitzaso, the woman he did
חליצה to.
Then ברק Barak dies in other words.
Yeah, ברק Barak died or divorced דבורה. Dvorah.
If ברק Barak dies, שמעון Shimon did חליצה with רחל Rachel and
then ברק Barak died.
Yeah, or divorced, or divorced.
Okay, so
for some reason although we understand why he can't have sex with
לאה, Leah, because that's a virtual ערוה, ervah, he also can't have
sex with דבורה, Dvorah, which doesn't seem to make any sense and
we'll see about that tomorrow.